AMAN S

aasharma0389@gmail.com

Summary

Analyst with almost 10 years of experience in delivering software products for the biggest educational, financial institutions and healthcare companies in USA and Canada. Led variety of analytics projects including building data science/machine learning pipelines, data warehouse development and analysis. Seeking a position where I can leverage my skills to build solutions that will empower leadership to make informed business decisions and provide avenues for new business opportunities

Skills

Big Data/Database: Spark, HQL, Impala, Oozie, SQL Server, Azure, Teradata, Oracle, MySQL, DB2, Vertica

Scripting/ Statistical Languages: Python, R, SQL, Perl, Shell, Matlab

Web Technologies: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript, Node.js, React.js, Express.js

BI Reporting Tools: Tableau, Power BI, SSRS, Business Objects

Relevant Work Experience

University of Toronto: Engagement Lead

2020 - Present

- Built logic to develop admission and retention data mart for student program of study (Major/Specialist). This
 strategic initiative aimed towards providing excellent services and world class education to students by analyzing vast
 dataset with complex rules across 3 major campuses
- Engaged with the user community consisting of 20 people to interview them, guide them through the agile process and develop a framework to manage the data lifecycle to build dashboards for student academic success
- Lead a team of 6 developers to move the university data assets to cutting edge Azure cloud platform
- Migrated the reporting logic to move the legacy cognos reports and cube to Tableau platform
- Designed azure architecture to automate data ingestion and ELT process to handle student data
- Made operational changes to the team to increase the efficiency and speed of delivery

Generali Global Health Services: Product Owner/Analyst

2019 – 2019

- Reduced operative costs by 20% through eliminating manual membership enrolment by implementing an industrystandard eligibility model for exchanging data with current and future international insurance, healthcare and TPA partners
- Led a team of QA and Analysts to create a new web and mobile interface for customers to update their information, take part in competition and give them a better digital experience
- Cut down time to process claims by moving from paper based approach to digital solution by allowing members to upload their claims receipt, medical reports through mobile
- Started an initiative to create an analytics team to build new predictive models and automate existing model at scale
- Improved the efficiency of the current multiple client on-boarding process by 50% through designing a highly scalable system on MS Azure
- Led the company's first initiative of evaluating its Net Promoter Score by developing a reporting logic based on business requirements to identify the company's areas of excellence and improvement
- Improved organizational data quality and reduced time to market by creating industry compliant data standards for ingestion of data by collaborating with internal stakeholders
- Implemented a company-wide Agile development model by advocating and introducing effective use of Jira and Confluence
- Performed QA for various projects and ensured 0 defects were encountered in production
- Managed product backlog, prioritized organizational needs and supervised project development by acting as a Product Owner for a scrum team

PointClickCare: Sr. Business Systems Analyst

2017 - 2018

- Performed requirements gathering from multiple product owners to understand EHR data needs
- Developed dashboards in Power BI for the new product that the company was rolling out to capture various KPIs
- Created a single source of truth for EHR data by designing enterprise data warehouse using enhanced e-r model
- Achieved and maintained >98% data accuracy by performing and supporting testing of the entire data platform across various environments

AMAN S

aasharma0389@gmail.com

- Created technical specifications and functional requirements by collaborating with engineers and product owners
- Implemented a process to maintain zero-defect standard in data export by coordinating and streamlining with external vendors
- Increased product quality and team collaboration while managing a team as a scrum master by applying Agile bestpractices
- Led a team of 4 to design automated testing framework to reduce testing effort from 6-7 hours to minutes
- Implemented automated unit test cases for the testing framework created
- Presented solutions to business stakeholders and technical architects to ensure data quality meets enterprise standards

Cigna: Sr. Systems Analyst

2015 - 2017

- Implemented text categorization model in R to solve multiclass classification problem to identify the category of complain the customer has made which was previously done manually. The automation gave a quick feedback to the customer excellence team to help them identify major areas of concern as opposed to a lag time of weeks. This implementation resulted in increased customer satisfaction as steps were taken immediately after the identification of the pain points
- Increased accuracy of finding patients with congestive heart failure who are at risk of re-hospitalization. The results of the model were used by case managers to create customized programs for these patients to improve their health and reduce re-hospitalization
- Developed KPI dashboards in Tableau for the sales and marketing team
- Increased the current data model accuracy by 5% in three months by building a self-learning framework which learns and processes from the most recent information
- Improved runtime of deployed models by ~15% by applying PCA and feature selection
- Oversaw a team of 4 to build statistical data model in Hadoop which led in early error detection and improved reporting accuracy on an average by 5%
- Migrated >600 statistical models in Spark-Hadoop environment as a lead systems analyst in a team of 4 analysts
- Increased Cigna's cost savings between 150-200 million dollars by year by leading a team who designed a fraud and abuse detection system through tracking provider geolocation and medical and pharmacy claim data correlation
- Refined requirements, and created ETL logic for very critical customer outreach program
- Converted requirements into specifications for the developers to create reporting layer for more than 100 reports
- Performed data analysis and profiling which resulted in around 10% increase in the accuracy of the reports
- Designed a very complex claim model consisting of millions of claims using Hadoop infrastructure.
- Served as a SME for various business, production and data related questions

Argus Information and Advisory Services: Sr. Analyst

2014 – 2015

Client: Top 3 bank in Eurozone

- Improved the current highly complex mortgage system's run time by 20% through system optimization
- Increased Argus' cost savings by approximately \$2M by identifying system gaps through data analysis and improving business rules of the system
- Wrote complex SQL queries to carry out the ETL process for creating the monthly federal risk report
- Ensured data accuracy of >99% by analysing submitted data and performing thorough validation of the existing business rules
- Created artefacts like mapping, modelling specification and business requirements documents
- Served as an SME for the home consumer line of business project track
- Interacted with the business partners to resolve any outstanding issues

Cigna: Sr. Systems Analyst

2014 - 2014

- Worked primarily with Pharmacy and Medical claims system and its integration with Cigna's Clinical IT data warehouse
- Worked with Type 1 and Type 2 dimensions, Fact tables, Operational Data Store and other warehousing concepts

AMAN S

aasharma0389@gmail.com

- Coordinated with the architect and modellers to understand the system architecture of Teradata environment
- Interacted with the internal customers to gather requirements for migration of ~2 petabytes of data
- Operated in a matrix and cross functional environment consisting of members from various realm of Cigna
- Documented the technical and mapping specification for raw loading of more than 60 tables
- Collaborated with the source team to create a smooth process for timely loads of the warehouse
- Created modelling document which required extensive understanding of the business needs
- Designed mapping document used by the developers as specifications for carrying out ETL
- Converted requirements into specifications for the developers to create reporting layer
- Served as a liaison between the business users and the developers
- Reviewed and signed-off test cases for performance and accurate data loads
- Assisted the QA team with any data related queries
- Contributed towards functional and non-functional requirements of the project

Fidelity Investments: Sr. BI Analyst

2013 - 2014

- Understood the warehouse system consisting more than 200 reports and dashboards
- Developed database migration plan for Microsoft SQL Server to Oracle database migration
- Wrote SQL queries to create proof of concept in oracle database
- Examined reports and pitched ideas for creating new reports/dashboards for better analysis of data
- Created document for visualization best practices and report and dashboard design
- Served as a conduit between the business and development team
- Involved in defining the source to target data mappings, business rules and data definitions
- Served as point of contact for user queries and production issues
- Worked with the project manager, architect and developers to develop the project timeline and plan
- Contributed towards documentation of business requirements for developing new reports

Argus Information and Advisory Services: Analyst

2013 - 2013

Client: Top 3 Bank in U.S.A

- Created new data model for the client which reduced the processing time from minutes to seconds
- Communicated with the architects and coordinated with the developers to come up with the system design
- Developed the database structure and also contributed extensively in writing queries that perform DDL and DML
- Loaded raw data files sized greater than 30 GB using Perl, Unix and SQL on Vertica platform in less than 10 minutes
- Applied SQL optimization and tuning techniques for fast retrieval of data
- Coded and owned more than 20 interfaces for data warehouse loading
- Processed monthly and daily files which involved processing data of more than 50 million users daily
- Supported and developed Perl modules on ad-hoc basis for automation of various processes
- Performed ETL using vSQL and Perl and was involved in the entire warehouse development cycle
- Monitored and worked with the developers to find the root cause of the data related issues
- Designed and documented the test cases for ensuring quality of data and performed thorough validation
- Automated activities like spooling, archival and transfer of data using shell scripts and Autosys
- Migrated data from development to testing region on Unix environment
- Created the MDD documents which required extensive knowledge of clients data fields, required for analytics
- Coached other team members and interns on the system architecture and technology

Education

University of Arizona, Management Information Systems
2011 – 2012
University of Mumbai, Bachelor of Engineering in Information Technology
2007 – 2011
Coursera, Machine Learning Classification/Regression (UW), Machine Learning (Stanford)
Avg. Grade: 99.4%